Guide to the Marie Scheikévitch Papers and Sicard Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Marie Scheikévitch Writings, 1900-1959; Series III; 0.74; (1.75 boxes)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - "Des échos sur 'Echo' de Violette Trefusis," book review, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 241)
    - Essay concerning a visit with Richmal Crompton, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 242)
    - "Histoire de ma vie, 'Apprentissage de la vie'," review of the autobiography of Queen Marie of Romania, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 243)
    - Novel, untitled, with notes and portfolio (Box 8, Folder 244-251)
    - Proust, Marcel. Lettres à Madame Scheikévitch, fragments of proofs, [ca. 1928] (Box 8, Folder 252)
    - Student notebooks and fragments, 1900, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 253-255)
    - Unidentified fragments and notes, 1911, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 256)
- Other Marie Scheikévitch Papers, 1902-1943; Series IV; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - Berthelot, Daniel. "Des voix dans la nuit," essay about telegraphy, holograph, signed, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 257)
  - Drawings, pencil, ink, and watercolor (Box 8, Folder 258-260)
  - Identity cards, with photographs of MS, 1937, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 261)
  - Martinie, Henri. Photograph of Aristide Briand, inscribed to MS
  - Notes concerning social engagements, 1902-34, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 262)
  - Photograph of Edmond Jaloux, inscribed to MS (Box 8, Folder 263)
  - Five photographs of MS and several unidentified people (Box 8, Folder 264)
- Sicard Family Papers, 1814-1979; Series V; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  - FRANCOIS SICARD PAPERS
    - Correspondence
      - "A-Z" General, 1915-30, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 265)
      - Aicard, Jean, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 266)
      - Alexandre, Arsène, 1924 Dec 23 (Box 9, Folder 267)
      - Aulard, F.-A. (François-Alphonse), 1910 Mar 26 (Box 9, Folder 268)
      - Barrias, Ernest, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 269)
      - Bouchard, Henri (FS to HB, photocopy), 1902 Jul [6?] (Box 9, Folder 270)
      - Charpentier, Gustave, 1930 Aug 21 (Box 9, Folder 271)
      - Claretie, Jules, 1905, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 272)
      - Clemenceau, Georges, 1923 Jul 27 (Box 9, Folder 273)
      - Courteline, Georges, 1916-26, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 274)
        Includes letters written for Courteline by his wife Marie-Jeanne; and single envelopes
      - Didon, Henri, 1890 Jun 14 (Box 9, Folder 275)
      - Doumergue, Gaston, [1930 Aug?] (Box 9, Folder 276)
      - Feydeau, Georges, 1903 [Feb 7?] (Box 9, Folder 277)
      - Foch, Ferdinand (photocopy), 1918 Aug 6 (Box 9, Folder 278)
      - Formont, Maxime, 19[1-?] Mar (Box 9, Folder 279)
      - France, Anatole, 1913-21 (Box 9, Folder 280)
      - Havard, Henry, 1903 Jan 31 (Box 9, Folder 281)
      - Jeanneney, Jean-Marcel, 1920, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 282)
        Includes a letter to Lili Scheikévitch Sicard
      - Martet, J., 1920 May 19 (Box 9, Folder 283)
        Written for Georges Clemenceau
      - Mercié, Antonin, 1894 Feb 15 (Box 9, Folder 284)
      - Meurice, Paul, 1904 Feb-Jun (Box 9, Folder 285)
      - Montaiglon, Anatole de, 1889-95, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 286)
        Includes poem: "Sur le prix de sculpture de M. Sicard en 1891"
      - Richepin, Jean, 1926 Apr 30 (Box 9, Folder 287)
      - Silvestre, Armand, 1897 Apr 13 (Box 9, Folder 288)
      - Tabarant, A. (Adolphe), 1934 Jul 4 (Box 9, Folder 289)
      - Veber, Pierre, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 290)
      - Willette, Adolphe, 1921, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 291)
      - ----- (sous-secrétariat d'État des Beaux Arts), 1908 Nov 24 (Box 9, Folder 292)
      - Unidentified, 1898-1931, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 293)
    - Other Papers
      - Drawings, sketches, and watercolors, 1909-33, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 294-296)
      - Ephemera and clippings, 1891-1931, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 297)
      - Legal documents concerning the Pinot family and a dispute over fishing rights, 1872 Apr 10 (Box 9, Folder 298)
      - Notes on the Russian language, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 299)
      - Photograph of an unidentified courtroom scene, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 300)
      - Visiting card, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 301)
  - PIERRE SICARD PAPERS
    - Correspondence
      - "A-Z" General, 1934-64 (Box 9, Folder 302)
      - Amiel, Denys, 1943 Mar 19 (Box 9, Folder 303)
      - Bondeville, Emmanuel (Box 9, Folder 304)
      - Clemenceau, A., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 305)
      - Clemenceau, Georges, 1928, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 306)
        Includes photograph reproductions of letters
      - Clemenceau-Jacquemaire, Madeleine, 1935 Jun-Jul (Box 9, Folder 307)
      - Dalzell Hatfield Galleries, 1954 Dec 27 (Box 9, Folder 308)
      - Druon, Maurice, 1976 [Nov?] 25 (Box 9, Folder 309)
      - Fels, Florent, 1949 [Mar?] 27 (Box 9, Folder 310)
      - Fleuret, Fernand, 1930-34 (Box 9, Folder 311)
        Includes letters to "Monsieur Dalmaü" and "Don Vicente" introducing PS
      - Gaillard, Marius-François, 1964 Mar 19 (Box 9, Folder 312)
        Accompanied by notes, outline, and synopsis of his ballet Adjuge! (ou Les folles enchères)
      - Garçon, Maurice, 1962 Oct 31 (Box 9, Folder 313)
      - Girard, André, 1963-64 (Box 9, Folder 314)
      - Green, Julien, [1977?] (Box 9, Folder 315)
      - Lanquest, ----- (notaire), 1930 Jan (Box 9, Folder 316)
        Concerns a bequest made by Georges Clemenceau to PS
      - Lanoux, Armand, 1978-79, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 317)
      - Lattre, maréchale de (wife of Jean de Lattre de Tassigny), 1962 Jan (Box 9, Folder 318)
      - Le Prieur, Yves (to Suzanne Sicard, wife of PS), 1949 Mar 24 (Box 9, Folder 319)
      - Monti, Jean, 1933, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 320)
      - Morand, Paul, 1968 Nov 20 (Box 9, Folder 321)
      - Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy (printed card), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 322)
      - Ormesson, Jean d', 1979, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 323)
      - Palewski, Gaston, 1979 May 16 (Box 9, Folder 324)
      - Pétain, Philippe (to révérend père Masquilier, concerning Henri Bicart, signed by Pétain's secretary), 1944 Feb 8 (Box 9, Folder 325)
      - Poher, Alain, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 326)
      - Rebaud, Henri, n.y. Jul 8 (Box 9, Folder 327)
      - Saint-Gaudens, Homer, 1938 Nov 10 (Box 9, Folder 328)
      - Scheikévitch, Marie, [1964?] (Box 9, Folder 329)
      - Sicard, François, 1914-29 (Box 9, Folder 330)
        Letters include postscripts by Lili Scheikévitch Sicard Accompanied by a letter from FS to an unidentified recipient
      - Sicard, Lili Scheikévitch, 1940 Jul 10 (Box 9, Folder 331)
      - [Silvy?], René, 1943-4[5?] (Box 9, Folder 332)
      - Valeri, Diego, 1963-68 (Box 9, Folder 333)
        Accompanied by biographical notes about DV
      - Winthrop, Grenville Lindall, 1936 Apr 27 (Box 9, Folder 334)
      - "Nino", 1922, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 335)
      - Unidentified, 1926-61, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 336)
    - Other Papers
      - Académie des Beaux-Arts. "Election d'un membre de la section sculpture...," printed form completed in manuscript, 1924 Feb 9 (Box 10, Folder 337)
      - Clemenceau, Georges. "Pendant le bal," play, holograph (Box 10, Folder 338)
      - Ephemera and clippings, 1906-78, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 339)
      - Order granting a military decoration to Charles Marie Victurnien, printed form completed in manuscript, 1814 Aug 27 (Box 10, Folder 340)
      - "Le voyage à Naples," song text, manuscript, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 341)
      - Fragments of travel diaries, 1929, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 342)
        Some possibly written by FS
- Oversize, 1912 Apr 10
  - Telegram, Adrien Hébrard to MS (in Series I), 1912 Apr 10 (Box Port, Folder 343)
  - Martinie, Henri. Photograph of Aristide Briand, inscribed to MS (in Series I) (Box Port, Folder 344)